Indiana University Libraries Assistant Director's records, 1960-1986 C541
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Libraries Assistant Director's records
1960-1986
1968-1979
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University, Bloomington. Libraries
C541
5.4 cubic feet 6 boxes
Wilmer H. Baatz served as the Assistant Library Director at Indiana University from 1966-1986. He was responsible for building up the Afro-American studies collection and the cooperative project between all IU campuses to allow faculty to borrow materials from all state universities. The collection consists of administrative records and corresponded related to Baatz's time as assistant director.
Access Restrictions
Select files are closed to researchers. Advance notice required for access.
Biographical Note/Administrative History
The library has long been an important institution at Indiana University with Theophilus A. Wylie serving as the first librarian of the university. Originally located in Wylie Hall, then Maxwell and Franklin Hall before the Main Library was opened in 1969 to meet the growing needs of students, staff, and faculty at the Bloomington campus. The library was originally built to house 2,600,000 volumes. In 2005, the library was renamed the Herman B Wells Library to honor the long-time support and dedication of IU president and chancellor Herman B Wells to the library.
Wilmer Henry Martin Baatz was born on October 23, 1915 in Fort Wayne, Indiana. In 1940, he earned his Bachelor of Arts degree, and in 1941 he earned his Master of Arts degree in English, both from Indiana University. During World War II, Baatz served in the U.S. Army Air Corps for three and half years. After the war, he attended the University of Chicago where be obtained his Library Science degree in 1946.
After graduate school, Baatz took a job as an Assistant Librarian at Beloit College in 1947. From 1949-1950 he worked as the Assistant Director of Libraries for the University of Rochester. He subsequently worked as the Chief of Technical Services at the Milwaukee Public Library from 1950-1955, as Supervisory Librarian for the Veterans Administration in Washington, D.C. from 1955-1960, and as the Chief Librarian of the Federal Aviation Agency from 1960-1965.
Baatz joined the Indiana University Library in 1965 as an Assistant Director and worked for the IU libraries for twenty years. During that time, he was responsible for recommending the cooperative library projects between the IU campuses that allowed faculty to use all state university library materials. He was also behind the idea to copy Bloomington library resources on film so that faculty and students at all campuses would have access to the same information. Baatz was knowledgeable about grant funds for libraries, and successfully helped to bring more than a half a million dollars in grant funding to Indiana University. Additionally, he worked to improve library resources for the Black Culture Center and the African-American Studies curriculum.
During the course of his career, he published more than thirty-four articles and books. He served as an officer or chairman of several professional organizations, such as the Indiana Library Association and the Special Libraries Association.
Baatz retired from librarianship in the spring of 1986, but continued to volunteer his time to the university by working part-time at the Black Culture Center. Wilmer Baatz passed away on February 21, 1991.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into one series, Administrative files.
Scope and Content Note
The collection is organized into a single series of Administrative files (1960-1986), which consists of records dating from Wilmer Baatz's tenure as Assistant Director of the IU Libraries. It contains information concerning library department committee meetings, correspondence with colleagues, information on various academic departments, and general files related to the management of the library system.
Separated Material
Five files were pulled from the Administrative Files series and placed in Restricted.
Related Material
Additional records such as newsletters, annual reports, bulletins, and publications may be accessed in the Archives of Institutional Memory
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database: Archive-It
Acquisition Information
Accessions 97/050, 2003/107, 2009/090
Provenance
Transferred from Lilly Library to the University Archives, July 2, 1997 and September 12, 1997.
Academic libraries --Indiana --Bloomington --History --20th century --Sources.; Indiana University, Bloomington. Libraries -- Archives; Indiana University, Bloomington. Libraries -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University, Bloomington. Libraries -- Administration -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Baatz, Wilmer H. -- Archives; Baatz, Wilmer H. -- Correspondence
- Administrative files, 1960-1986; undated (Box 1)
  - Afro-American Rare Books, 1971-1984 (Box 1)
  - Afro-American Studies, 1967-1986 (Box 1)
  - Annual Report (Box 1)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Archives of Traditional Music, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Association of Research Libraries (ARL), 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Automation, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Baatz, William, Search Committees, 1971 (Box 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted
  - Ball State University Library, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Biology Library (Box 1)
    - 1965-1976 (Box 1)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Bloomington Faculty Council, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Bob Knight Library Fund, 1975-1981 (Box 1)
  - Branch Hourly, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Branches, New, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Budget Comparisons, 1977-1979 (Box 1)
  - Budget Conference, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Budget Revisions, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Business Library, 1965-1971 (Box 1)
  - Business Library, 1966-1979 (Box 1)
  - Byrd, Cecil K. - Surveys, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Carrels, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry, 1966-1977 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - College and Research Libraries Report, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Combined Head of Department Meetings, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Cooperation, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Baatz, 1965-1981 (Box 2)
  - Cost Studies, 1962-1980 (Box 2)
  - Council of Branch Librarians, 1979-1982 (Box 2)
  - Counterpart Groups, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Daily Student, 1965-1968 (Box 2)
  - Dean Candidates, undated (Box 2)
  - De Capo Press, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Dental Library, 1966-1971 (Box 2)
  - Department Heads Meeting, 1973-1976 (Box 2)
  - Discriminatory Practices, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Education - Faculty Library Handbook, undated (Box 2)
  - Energy Emergency, 1978 (Box 2)
  - ERIC/CRIER (Educational Resource Information Center, 1968-1972 (Box 2)
  - ERIC Program, Office of Education, 1966-1972 (Box 2)
  - Fine Arts Library (Box 2)
    - 1964-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1966-1972 (Box 2)
  - Fire (Box 2)
    - February 17, 1969 (Box 2)
    - January 5, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Geography, 1968-1979 (Box 2)
  - Geology, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Geology Library, 1966-1979 (Box 2)
  - Graham, Peter, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Gifts, 1971-1982 (Box 2)
  - Graduate Library School - Integration with Main Library, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Handicapped, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - Higher Education General Informational Survey (HEGIS) Report, 1977 (Box 2)
  - HPER (Box 2)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1978 (Box 2)
  - Indiana Commission for Higher Commission (ICHE), 1972 (Box 3)
  - Indiana Higher Education Telecommunication System (IHETS), 1970-1977 (Box 3)
  - Indiana Cooperative Library Services Authority (INCOLSA), 1978-1981 (Box 3)
  - IU East Report, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Indiana State Library, 1967-1976 (Box 3)
  - Indiana Library Association, 1974-1980 (Box 3)
  - Indiana University Library Association (InULA), 1973-1981 (Box 3)
  - Indiana University Library School, 1963-1979 (Box 3)
  - Indiana University News Notes, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Indiana University Publications, 1966-1978 (Box 3)
  - Indiana University School of Medicine Library, 1968-1978 (Box 3)
  - Indiana University Tustees Notes, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Indiana University – Purdue University Indianapolis (I.U.P.U.I.) (Box 3)
    - General, 1969-1981 (Box 3)
    - Library Coordinating Committee, 1979-1981 (Box 3)
  - Instruction and Orientation, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Instructional Media Services Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Jackson Retirement, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Journalism, 1974-1979 (Box 3)
  - Knox College Newsletter, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Labeling, Title Page, Margins, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Library Advisory Committee (LAC), 1973 (Box 3)
  - Latin American Studies, 1976-1978 (Box 3)
  - Law Library (Box 3)
    - Indianapolis, 1967-1976 (Box 3)
    - Bloomington, 1971-1977 (Box 3)
  - Library Faculty, 1973-1980 (Box 3)
  - I.U. Library Faculty Newsletter, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Library Materials Budget, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - Library of Congress, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - Library Technician Program, undated (Box 3)
  - Lilly Library, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Loan Prices Task, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Long Range Plans, undated (Box 3)
  - Management Review and Analysis Program (Box 3)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - 1974-1976 (Box 3)
    - August 1, 1974- January 9, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Medical Sciences Library, 1965-1979 (Box 3)
  - Miller,Dr. Robert A., 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Music Library (Box 4)
    - 1966-1973 (Box 4)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 4)
  - National Commission on Libraries and Information Science (NCLIS), 1970-1973 (Box 4)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH), 1977 (Box 4)
  - National Library of Medicine, 1979 (Box 4)
  - New Library Building, 1965-1970 (Box 4)
  - New Library Building II, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    General
    2 photos removed
  - New York University Library, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Non-Book Subcommittee, 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - Non-Library Systems Libraries, 1979 (Box 4)
  - North Central Association (NCA) Decennial Evaluation, 1976 (Box 4)
  - OCLC, 1975-1981 (Box 4)
  - Off-Print Survey, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Ohio Valley Group of Technical Service Librarians, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Optometry Library, 1966-1979 (Box 4)
  - Overstreet, Bonaro, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Parking Money, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Personnel, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - Personnel II, 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - Philiippine-Barangay Club of Indiana, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Planning, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Planter for Lobby, 1978 (Box 4)
  - President's Council on the Humanities, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Priorities for IUB Libraries (correspondence), 1966-1977 (Box 4)
  - Professional Criteria, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Proposal for a Center for Fine Arts Resources at Indiana University, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Public Services, 1977-1980 (Box 4)
  - Purdue University Libraries (correspondence), 1966-1977 (Box 4)
  - Questionnaires, 1965-1974 (Box 4)
  - Reprints, 1969-1977 (Box 4)
  - Research Coordination and Development Liaison Group, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Science Information Exchange, 1967-1969 (Box 4)
  - Security, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Sex Institute, 1972-1979 (Box 5)
  - Special Libraries Association (SLA), 1965-1973 (Box 5)
  - Social Services Library, 1967 (Box 5)
  - School of Public and Environmental Affairs (S.P.E.A.), 1974-1977 (Box 5)
  - Staff Meetings, 1969-1973 (Box 5)
  - State University Director's Meeting (Box 5)
    - General, October 1971 (Box 5)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 5)
    - 1975-1979 (Box 5)
    - Annual Meeting, 1968-1971 (Box 5)
  - Student Affairs, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Student Employment, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Student Government, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Support Staff, 1973-1979 (Box 5)
  - Surplus Materials Center, 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - Swain Hall Library, 1965-1977 (Box 5)
  - Technical Services, 1978-1981 (Box 5)
  - Theses, 1964-1977 (Box 5)
  - Three-millionth Volume, 1977 (Box 5)
  - Title IIC, 1978-1979 (Box 5)
  - Undergraduate Library (Box 5)
    - 1960 (Box 5)
    - 1971-1976 (Box 5)
  - Undergraduate Library Brand Diary, 1961 (Box 5)
  - Undergraduate Library Study, 1978 (Box 5)
  - University Library Committee, 1968-1981 (Box 5)
  - Use Studies, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Vocational Education, 1977-1978 (Box 5)
  - Women, 1981 (Box 5)
  - Xerox, 1967-1976 (Box 5)
  - Restricted Files, undated (Box 6)